<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Greenspace on Researcher</title>
    <link>/tags/greenspace/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Greenspace on Researcher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/greenspace/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to quickly visualise massive spatio-temporal data? Experiences with Kepler.gl</title>
      <link>/post/kepler/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/kepler/</guid>
      <description>Background Are you collecting lots of geospatial data and need a way to quickly visualise what you’ve got? Read on!
I had this problem; I was collecting a lot of information on my daily movements from Arc App: Location and Activity (more on the use of Arc for research later). Additionally, I wanted to quickly see what features of the urban environment (e.g. greenspaces) I was being ‘exposed’ to. The solution was Uber’s open source geospatial analysis tool: Kepler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/project/mmp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/mmp/</guid>
      <description>Our health and mobility are intrinsically linked with the quality of our local environment. All sorts of things affect us, from housing density and neighbourhood deprivation to access to green space. In Topic 3, we have explored how physical, built and social environments evolve over time and how they impact on inequalities in health in older age, related to mobility throughout life. We have used data from just under 600 people in their 70’s, together with long term, area-level measures of their childhood, adulthood and current environment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>