<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Processing on Researcher</title>
    <link>/categories/data-processing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Processing on Researcher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/data-processing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build a Social Fragmentation Index using census variables</title>
      <link>/post/social-fragmentation-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/social-fragmentation-index/</guid>
      <description>Background The Social Fragmentation Index (SFI) was developed by Peter Congdon. The indicator aims to use census variables to capture (for small areas across the country) aspects of the local population that may reflect a greater collective risk of social fragmentation/lack of social cohesion. The census variables are proxies for these risk factors, rather than ‘direct’ indicators. It focusses on risk due to potentially high levels of isolation and residential instability of members of the population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the optional courses like for UoE MSc students?</title>
      <link>/post/msccourses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/msccourses/</guid>
      <description>The aim was to understand more about the optional courses available for MSc students in the school of Geosciences. This meant building a dataframe that contained the interesting bits of information available on the University of Edinburgh website so that I could query it to find out answers to questions such as: How many 10 credit courses are available? Which degree cluster do the courses belong to and is there any overlap?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Earth Engine: NDVI in Scotland 2001-2017</title>
      <link>/post/gee/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gee/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Motivation I’m interested in a long-term small-area level measure of ‘green spaces’, features of the natural environment that are important for a wide variety of health outcomes.
 Green spaces over time There are two major green space datasets for Scotland, Scotland’s Greenspace Map 2011 and the Ordnance Survey’s Greenspace Map 2017. These maps were produced by characterising OS polygons using aerial photos, with the latter updated every 6 months from July 2017.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NetCDF in R</title>
      <link>/post/netcdf-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/netcdf-in-r/</guid>
      <description>NetCDF stands for “Network Common Data Format” and was created by ‘unidata’ for handling large geospatial data. Here’s a short description from their website:
“NetCDF is a set of software libraries and self-describing, machine-independent data formats that support the creation, access, and sharing of array-orientated scientific data.”
NetCDF files are containers for dimensions, variables and global atttributes. It’s used to store climatology, meteorology and oceanography data by over 1,300 organisations including NOAA and EUMETSAT.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStreetMap in R</title>
      <link>/post/osmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/osmr/</guid>
      <description>I found a really helpful tutorial on using OpenStreetMap data in R the other day.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>