<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researcher on Researcher</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Researcher on Researcher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DISPLAY</title>
      <link>/project/display/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/display/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>/post/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;welcome&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Welcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my first post. As an avid R user, I was amazed at how quickly it was to setup a static website with the help from the R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;“blogdown”&lt;/a&gt;. I thought Yihui Xie gave a convincing argument for blogging from his personal experience (Appendix D in above website). In summary he provides three reasons in favour of blogging:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To consolidate thoughts and create a clearer argument for topics that are important to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To engage with other people and get helpful feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To remember things that you have done so that they can be re-used in new applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are things that I already try to do, albeit unsystematically. I find that the things I do in this respect are either quite time consuming (e.g. giving a tutorial or presentation) or fleeting (e.g. conversations with friends and family), and a blog fits nicely in between. With respect to the third point I have a github repository for &lt;a href=&#34;%22https://github.com/markocherrie/Helpful_Code%22&#34;&gt;helpful code&lt;/a&gt;, however this tends to be more of a dump of code snippets rather than a thoughtful write-up of what I was doing. So this website fits in nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned that this is a static website in the first paragraph. This terminology was completely new to me when I started to set this site up. A static website is one that has every webpage stored as a single file on the server, e.g. this post has it’s own HTML (Hypertext Markup Language) file associated with it. Hugo, Jeykll and Hexo are the static site generators that you pass these files to. The main advantage to static websites is that you can hit the ground running, a little bit of HTML and CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) knowledge can go a long way. There is no requirement to know any server side scripting languages such a PHP (Hypertext Preprocessor) or SQL (Structured Query Language), which means there is no server-host interaction and therefore load times are very quick. There are drawbacks though. If you intend to change something on every page, then this can be very time consuming. There is also a lot less functionality than a dynamic page which can add features such as shopping carts and social media interactions. Another option would have been to use a CMS (Content Management System) such as Joomla or Wordpress, beating both static and dynamic on ease of setup and time to update. Although I think that their functionality is a black box and if you want to deviate from the default template then you may get unstuck. CMS’s have got around this by adding plugins. However I have found that often these aren’t available on the cheaper pricing tiers. For example Wordpress does not allow you to use iframe (a webpage inside another webpage…webception) and the plugin is only available on the business pricing tier (£20.83 a month). So I’d argue that a static website for a blog is a good option, which allows the website to grow as the webmaster’s skills do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all my posts, I’ll be writing from memory, from my own experiences, which may have not been remembered correctly or do not include the full picture. If you think there should be an improvement to the post then please get in touch and I’ll update it, I’m always willing to learn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post: On static, dynamic and CMS websites</title>
      <link>/post/first-post-on-static-dynamic-and-cms-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/first-post-on-static-dynamic-and-cms-websites/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;welcome&#34;&gt;Welcome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my first post. As an avid R user, I was amazed at how quickly it was to setup a static website with the help from the R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;blogdown&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I though Yihui Xie gave a convincing argument for blogging from his personal experience (Appendix D in above website). IN summary he provides three reasons for being in favour of blogging:
* To consolidate thoughts and create a clearer argument for topics that are important to you.
* To engage with other people and get helpful feedback.
* To remember things that you have done so that they can be re-used in new applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already try to do the first two points in my day-to-day life, although what I find is that they are either quite time consuming (e.g. giving a tutorial or presentation) or fleeting (e.g. conversations with friends and family), a blog fits nicely in between. I have started to make progress on the third point by having a github repository for [helpful code](&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/markocherrie/Helpful_Code&amp;quot;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/markocherrie/Helpful_Code&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;) but this tends to be more of a dump of things that I have found useful rather than&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rshiny Weather App</title>
      <link>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(reshape2)
x&amp;lt;-44 + 12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alcohol and Tobacco Environments in Scotland</title>
      <link>/project/webmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/webmap/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing the Association between Ultraviolet Radiation, Vitamin D and Allergic Disease</title>
      <link>/project/uv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/uv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exposure to vitamin D effective ultraviolet radiation (UVvitd) is key to the
production of vitamin D in human skin. Ambient ultraviolet radiation, dietary intake
of D3/D2 and 25-hydroxy vitamin D in serum and saliva have been used as a proxy
for vitamin D status. However, these exposures have yet to yield a consistent
effect on allergic diseases. The aim of the thesis was to determine the spatiotemporal
distribution of UVvitd and 25(OH)D in Britain, so as to investigate the
effect on allergic health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relative effectiveness of known determinants of UVvitd and 25(OH)D
(latitude and month of the year) and proposed determinants (longitude, elevation,
urban/rural residence, coastal residence, year of blood measurement, day of
blood measurement/year) were described. Coastal residence was shown to
be a novel geographic determinant of higher levels of UVvitd and 25(OH)D in
England and may help to explain previous associations with general health and
wellbeing. Further to these results, the relationship between UVvitd and 25(OH)D
was investigated. This stimulated the development of an instrumental variable,
which can be used to reduce the effect of confounding in observational studies.
Common meteorological data including sunshine duration and temperature were
used to predict ambient UVvitd at a postcode sector level. The ambient UVvitd
instrument was shown to linearly predict 25(OH)D, measured in the 1958 Birth
Cohort participants aged 45, at three and six month cumulative doses before
blood measurement. Effectiveness was attenuated by the duration of outdoor
activity. The relationship between ambient UVvitd and 25(OH)D was used to
estimate the effect of maternal 25(OH)D on hay fever, eczema and asthma in
childhood. Consistent positive associations were found with hay fever only. There
may have been beneficial differential effect on asthma by atopic status and sex
of the participant. In males with hay fever asthma prevalence was lowest in the
highest UVvitd quartile. However the marker of atopy was weak (i.e. parental
reported hay fever) and the interaction was insignificant (i.e. p=0.07). Therefore,
the association between 25(OH)D and asthma prevalence and incidence was
investigated, with atopic status determined using a mixture of self-reported and
biomedical data (i.e. IgE measurements) from the 1958 Birth Cohort in adulthood.
The interaction between 25(OH)D and atopic status was highly significant and non-atopic individuals were shown to have an increased risk of asthma for
every 10 nmol/l decrease in 25(OH)D. Given that vitamin D represents only one
health effect of human interactions with climate, the relationship between several
meteorological variables and GP prevalence rates of asthma was investigated.
A combination of high UVvitd and temperature and low relative humidity and
precipitation was associated with lower asthma prevalence.
To summarise, the findings have determined that UVvitd varies geographically
and temporally with 25(OH)D in Britain and higher levels could benefit specific
subtypes of allergic disease. By utilising multiple existing meteorological data,
the understanding of the aetiology of allergic disease can be advanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental determinants of IVF treatment</title>
      <link>/project/ivf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/ivf/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Medical &amp; Environmental Data Mash-up Infrastructure project (MEDMI)</title>
      <link>/project/medmi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/medmi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobility, Mood and Place</title>
      <link>/project/mmp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/mmp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gcushen.github.io/hugo-academic-demo/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;r-markdown&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;R Markdown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see &lt;a href=&#34;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can embed an R code chunk like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(cars)
##      speed           dist       
##  Min.   : 4.0   Min.   :  2.00  
##  1st Qu.:12.0   1st Qu.: 26.00  
##  Median :15.0   Median : 36.00  
##  Mean   :15.4   Mean   : 42.98  
##  3rd Qu.:19.0   3rd Qu.: 56.00  
##  Max.   :25.0   Max.   :120.00
fit &amp;lt;- lm(dist ~ speed, data = cars)
fit
## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = dist ~ speed, data = cars)
## 
## Coefficients:
## (Intercept)        speed  
##     -17.579        3.932&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;including-plots&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Including Plots&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also embed plots. See Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pie&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;par(mar = c(0, 1, 0, 1))
pie(
  c(280, 60, 20),
  c(&amp;#39;Sky&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Sunny side of pyramid&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Shady side of pyramid&amp;#39;),
  col = c(&amp;#39;#0292D8&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#F7EA39&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#C4B632&amp;#39;),
  init.angle = -50, border = NA
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:pie&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown_files/figure-html/pie-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;A fancy pie chart.&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: A fancy pie chart.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coastal climate is associated with elevated solar irradiance and higher serum vitamin D levels</title>
      <link>/publication/uv/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/uv/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
