<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researcher on Researcher</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Researcher on Researcher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DISPLAY</title>
      <link>/project/display/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/display/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rshiny Weather App</title>
      <link>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(reshape2)
x&amp;lt;-44 + 12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alcohol and Tobacco Environments in Scotland</title>
      <link>/project/webmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/webmap/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing the Association between Ultraviolet Radiation, Vitamin D and Allergic Disease</title>
      <link>/project/uv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/uv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exposure to vitamin D effective ultraviolet radiation (UVvitd) is key to the
production of vitamin D in human skin. Ambient ultraviolet radiation, dietary intake
of D3/D2 and 25-hydroxy vitamin D in serum and saliva have been used as a proxy
for vitamin D status. However, these exposures have yet to yield a consistent
effect on allergic diseases. The aim of the thesis was to determine the spatiotemporal
distribution of UVvitd and 25(OH)D in Britain, so as to investigate the
effect on allergic health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relative effectiveness of known determinants of UVvitd and 25(OH)D
(latitude and month of the year) and proposed determinants (longitude, elevation,
urban/rural residence, coastal residence, year of blood measurement, day of
blood measurement/year) were described. Coastal residence was shown to
be a novel geographic determinant of higher levels of UVvitd and 25(OH)D in
England and may help to explain previous associations with general health and
wellbeing. Further to these results, the relationship between UVvitd and 25(OH)D
was investigated. This stimulated the development of an instrumental variable,
which can be used to reduce the effect of confounding in observational studies.
Common meteorological data including sunshine duration and temperature were
used to predict ambient UVvitd at a postcode sector level. The ambient UVvitd
instrument was shown to linearly predict 25(OH)D, measured in the 1958 Birth
Cohort participants aged 45, at three and six month cumulative doses before
blood measurement. Effectiveness was attenuated by the duration of outdoor
activity. The relationship between ambient UVvitd and 25(OH)D was used to
estimate the effect of maternal 25(OH)D on hay fever, eczema and asthma in
childhood. Consistent positive associations were found with hay fever only. There
may have been beneficial differential effect on asthma by atopic status and sex
of the participant. In males with hay fever asthma prevalence was lowest in the
highest UVvitd quartile. However the marker of atopy was weak (i.e. parental
reported hay fever) and the interaction was insignificant (i.e. p=0.07). Therefore,
the association between 25(OH)D and asthma prevalence and incidence was
investigated, with atopic status determined using a mixture of self-reported and
biomedical data (i.e. IgE measurements) from the 1958 Birth Cohort in adulthood.
The interaction between 25(OH)D and atopic status was highly significant and non-atopic individuals were shown to have an increased risk of asthma for
every 10 nmol/l decrease in 25(OH)D. Given that vitamin D represents only one
health effect of human interactions with climate, the relationship between several
meteorological variables and GP prevalence rates of asthma was investigated.
A combination of high UVvitd and temperature and low relative humidity and
precipitation was associated with lower asthma prevalence.
To summarise, the findings have determined that UVvitd varies geographically
and temporally with 25(OH)D in Britain and higher levels could benefit specific
subtypes of allergic disease. By utilising multiple existing meteorological data,
the understanding of the aetiology of allergic disease can be advanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental determinants of IVF treatment</title>
      <link>/project/ivf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/ivf/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Medical &amp; Environmental Data Mash-up Infrastructure project (MEDMI)</title>
      <link>/project/medmi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/medmi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobility, Mood and Place</title>
      <link>/project/mmp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/mmp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gcushen.github.io/hugo-academic-demo/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;r-markdown&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;R Markdown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see &lt;a href=&#34;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can embed an R code chunk like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(cars)
##      speed           dist       
##  Min.   : 4.0   Min.   :  2.00  
##  1st Qu.:12.0   1st Qu.: 26.00  
##  Median :15.0   Median : 36.00  
##  Mean   :15.4   Mean   : 42.98  
##  3rd Qu.:19.0   3rd Qu.: 56.00  
##  Max.   :25.0   Max.   :120.00
fit &amp;lt;- lm(dist ~ speed, data = cars)
fit
## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = dist ~ speed, data = cars)
## 
## Coefficients:
## (Intercept)        speed  
##     -17.579        3.932&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;including-plots&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Including Plots&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also embed plots. See Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pie&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;par(mar = c(0, 1, 0, 1))
pie(
  c(280, 60, 20),
  c(&amp;#39;Sky&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Sunny side of pyramid&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Shady side of pyramid&amp;#39;),
  col = c(&amp;#39;#0292D8&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#F7EA39&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#C4B632&amp;#39;),
  init.angle = -50, border = NA
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:pie&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown_files/figure-html/pie-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;A fancy pie chart.&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: A fancy pie chart.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coastal climate is associated with elevated solar irradiance and higher serum vitamin D levels</title>
      <link>/publication/uv/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/uv/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
