<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Researcher</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Researcher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we measure everyday exposure to greenspaces?</title>
      <link>/post/everydaygreen/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/everydaygreen/</guid>
      <description>How can we estimate exposure to the natural environment day-to-day?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build a structural equation model in Lavaan?</title>
      <link>/post/sem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sem/</guid>
      <description>Background I went on a course in Cambridge over the summer of 2018. This was to get me up to speed on structural equation modelling (SEM), which has a lot of potential applications in scenarios where the pathways between measured and unmeasured variables are the central focus of the research question.
 What is SEM? SEM is a mixture of confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and path analysis. Another way to describe that, is that you have a measurement part and a structural part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to quickly visualise massive spatio-temporal data?</title>
      <link>/post/kepler/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/kepler/</guid>
      <description>Background Are you collecting lots of geospatial data and need a way to quickly visualise what you’ve got? Read on! I had this problem; I was collecting a lot of information on my daily movements from Arc App: Location and Activity (more on the use of Arc for research later). Additionally, I wanted to quickly see what features of the urban environment (e.g. greenspaces) I was being ‘exposed’ to. The solution was Uber’s open source geospatial analysis tool: Kepler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to make teaching/outreach more interactive?</title>
      <link>/post/mentimeter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mentimeter/</guid>
      <description>Background I am keen to employ technology to assist in teaching. I went to the Social Science and Medicine Annual Scientific meeting in Glasgow last September and noticed that they were using software to get responses from the audience. The software was called Mentimeter. It turns out there has been a paper published by researchers from the University of Glasgow on the merits of interactive polling for teaching. The authors summarise that experiences of this technology are generally positive but caution that future use should focus first on the pedagogical approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we understand patterns of prescription use?</title>
      <link>/post/sequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sequence/</guid>
      <description>Background Longitudinal analysis is important as due to the temporal sequence of exposure then outcome, we can make a stronger case for causality. A derivative of a class of models that fit into the ‘data-mining’ family is sequence analysis. One use of this model is to understand lifetime states, e.g. being employed, being in education, being retired. By understanding these state sequences we can understand how the duration and timing of a state can affect health in the long term.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to find the optimal number of groups in GBTM?</title>
      <link>/post/gbtm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbtm/</guid>
      <description>Background Group-based trajectory modelling (GBMT) is a way of identifying latent patterns of change from multiple individual trajectories. It is widely used within the field of economics and also becoming popular in health geography. The process of deciding the number of classes is not transparent and tends to be based on one or two model fit statistics. Klijn et al., created a fit-criteria assessment plot (F-CAP) that accepts universal data input to aid the decision on the number of classes (2017).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Fragmentation Index</title>
      <link>/post/sfi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sfi/</guid>
      <description>BackgroundThe Social Fragmentation Index (SFI) was developed by Peter Congdon. The indicator aims to use census variables to capture (for small areas across the country) aspects of the local population that may reflect a greater collective risk of social fragmentation/lack of social cohesion. The census variables are proxies for these risk factors, rather than ‘direct’ indicators. It focusses on risk due to potentially high levels of isolation and residential instability of members of the population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the optional courses like for UoE MSc students?</title>
      <link>/post/msccourses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/msccourses/</guid>
      <description>The aim was to understand more about the optional courses available for MSc students in the school of Geosciences. This meant building a dataframe that contained the interesting bits of information available on the University of Edinburgh website so that I could query it to find out answers to questions such as: How many 10 credit courses are available? Which degree cluster do the courses belong to and is there any overlap?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Earth Engine: NDVI in Scotland 2001-2017</title>
      <link>/post/gee/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gee/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionMotivationI’m interested in a long-term small-area level measure of ‘green spaces’, features of the natural environment that are important for a wide variety of health outcomes.
Green spaces over timeThere are two major green space datasets for Scotland, Scotland’s Greenspace Map 2011 and the Ordnance Survey’s Greenspace Map 2017. These maps were produced by characterising OS polygons using aerial photos, with the latter updated every 6 months from July 2017.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Devolved parliaments and assemblies Legislation</title>
      <link>/post/devolvedlegislation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/devolvedlegislation/</guid>
      <description>Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland have had devolved powers since 1997, 1997 and 1998 respectively. During this time 480 Acts have been passed, an act being defined as primary legislation which has been through several stages from:
Pre-legislative scrutiny on the draft piece of legislation (bill)First Reading - first presentation, no votingSecond Reading - debate on principles, votingCommittee Stage - Considers bill clausesConsideration or report stage - Consider further amendmentsThird Reading - Consider final textPassage - Sent to other house (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NetCDF in R</title>
      <link>/post/netcdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/netcdf/</guid>
      <description>NetCDF stands for “Network Common Data Format” and was created by ‘unidata’ for handling large geospatial data. Here’s a short description from their website:
“NetCDF is a set of software libraries and self-describing, machine-independent data formats that support the creation, access, and sharing of array-orientated scientific data.”
NetCDF files are containers for dimensions, variables and global atttributes. It’s used to store climatology, meteorology and oceanography data by over 1,300 organisations including NOAA and EUMETSAT.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nudging people to make healthy behaviour choices</title>
      <link>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</guid>
      <description>Nudge theory made it big after the 2008 book by Thaler and Sunstein gathered some high profile readers (Obama, Cameron etc). Alongside public health officials and politicians, researchers have been interested in using the theory to influence people to make ‘healthy’ behaviour choices. The central tenant of the theory is based around libertarian paternalism, or influencing an individual’s ‘choice architecture’ without coercion. Nudge-type interventions (e.g. nutritional labeling, size of serving dishes) have been used to tackle obesity and were found to increase ‘healthy’ behaviours by 15.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Green Space and Traffic in Glasgow</title>
      <link>/post/greentraffic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/greentraffic/</guid>
      <description>Background The health benefit of greater availability of greenspaces is mediated by the quality of these spaces (Zhang et al., 2017). Recently, quality was associated with psychological distress, whereas availability had no effect (Feng and Astell-Burt, 2018). Both of these measures of quality were self-reported. Another method to determine quality is from GIS-derived measures of land use. Perhaps the optimal method is using questionnaire self-report and GIS-derived measures as has been developed by (Stessens et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Removing pages from a PDF</title>
      <link>/post/pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/pdf/</guid>
      <description>More of a note than a post but hopefully this can help someone else out having the same issue.
I needed to remove a couple of pages from a PDF document today. This can be done easily on a mac using preview (i.e. backspace when the page thumbnail is highlighted) but I couldn’t find a way on the PC, using my default PDF reader- Acrobat Reader DC. It seems that most of the useful functionality requires the pro version.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapzen Isochrone Maps</title>
      <link>/post/isochrone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/isochrone/</guid>
      <description>I have just come across Mapzen’s routing engine (Valhalla), which can be used to produce incredible isochrone maps, mentioned in this blog post. If you’ve not heard of Mapzen they provide mapping tools for developers so that their websites can be converted to the spatial side. The neat thing about isochrone lines is that they show the boundary around a point where travel time is equal. So you can ask some interesting proximity based questions (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>/post/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/first-post/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my first post. As an avid R user, I was amazed at how quickly it was to setup a static website with the help from the R package: “blogdown”. I thought Yihui Xie gave a convincing argument for blogging from his personal experience (Appendix D in above website). In summary he provides three reasons in favour of blogging:
To consolidate thoughts and create a clearer argument for topics that are important to you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStreetMap in R</title>
      <link>/post/osmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/osmr/</guid>
      <description>I found a really helpful tutorial on using OpenStreetMap data in R the other day.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>