<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Researcher</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Researcher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Removing pages from a PDF</title>
      <link>/post/pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/pdf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More of a note than a post but hopefully this can help someone else out having the same issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed to remove a couple of pages from a PDF document today. This can be done easily on a mac using preview (i.e. backspace when the page thumbnail is highlighted) but I couldn’t find a way on the PC, using my default PDF reader- Acrobat Reader DC. It seems that most of the useful functionality requires the pro version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first tried to edit it in GIMP (opensource photo editing software). I was able to import each of the PDF pages as layers and delete the layers I didn’t need. However, I couldn’t find a way of exporting properly, all I got was the first page. I did see something about saving it as a .mng and using inkscape/imagemagick’s ‘convert’ command but it seemed like a bit of work. Next up, LibreOffice, I saw an article describing that it was possible to import and edit a PDF using this software. This worked well, and was very intuitive, however when I looked at the exported PDF document it had made all the pages portrait. This was a problem as my some of my pages with wide table were landscape, so it had clipped them. Not being able to find a way to rotate individual pages in libreOffice (there must be a way of doing this!), I tried a final option to use a google drive extension- DocHub. This worked so well and made it really easy to save back to my Google drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you need some powerful software to edit a PDF quickly, check out [DocHub] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dochub.com&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://dochub.com&lt;/a&gt;)! Just beware that it’s only free up to a point. You can view and edit up to 2,000 documents, sign 5 documents/month, request up to 3 signers/month and email up to 3 documents/day, anything over this and you will need to go onto the pro account.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapzen Isochrone Maps</title>
      <link>/post/isochrone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/isochrone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just come across Mapzen’s routing engine (Valhalla), which can be used to produce incredible isochrone maps, mentioned in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://mapzen.com/blog/introducing-isochrone-service/&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. If you’ve not heard of &lt;a href=&#34;https://mapzen.com/&#34;&gt;Mapzen&lt;/a&gt; they provide mapping tools for developers so that their websites can be converted to the spatial side. The neat thing about isochrone lines is that they show the boundary around a point where travel time is equal. So you can ask some interesting proximity based questions (e.g. What types of greenspace do I have within a 5 minute walk from my home?). I’ve been eager to create isochrone maps since seeing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rome2rio.com/blog/2016/01/08/time-flies-according-to-these-maps-it-does/&#34;&gt;Rome2Rio’s set&lt;/a&gt;, which show isochrones from London for 1914 and 2016. Below I have used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mapzen.com/mobility/explorer/&#34;&gt;mobility explorer&lt;/a&gt; to generate isochrones boundaries (in 15 minute bands) for where I live, for several different travel options (walking, cycling, public transport and driving). Have a go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/mapzenimages/walking.png&#34; alt=&#34;Walking&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;img/mapzenimages/cycling.png&#34; alt=&#34;Cycling&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;img/mapzenimages/transit.png&#34; alt=&#34;Public Transport&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;img/mapzenimages/driving.png&#34; alt=&#34;Driving&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all my posts, I’m writing from memory, from my own experiences, which may have not been remembered correctly or do not include the full picture. If you think there should be an improvement to the post then please get in touch and I’ll update it, I’m always willing to learn!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>/post/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my first post. As an avid R user, I was amazed at how quickly it was to setup a static website with the help from the R package: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;“blogdown”&lt;/a&gt;. I thought Yihui Xie gave a convincing argument for blogging from his personal experience (Appendix D in above website). In summary he provides three reasons in favour of blogging:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To consolidate thoughts and create a clearer argument for topics that are important to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To engage with other people and get helpful feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To remember things that you have done so that they can be re-used in new applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are things that I already try to do, albeit unsystematically. I find that the things I do in this respect are either quite time consuming (e.g. giving a tutorial or presentation) or fleeting (e.g. conversations with friends and family). With respect to the third point I have a github repository for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/markocherrie/Helpful_Code&#34;&gt;helpful code&lt;/a&gt;, however this tends to be more of a dump of code snippets rather than a thoughtful write-up of what I was doing. So this website fits in nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned that this is a static website in the first paragraph. This terminology was completely new to me when I started to set this site up. A static website is one that has every webpage stored as a single file on the server, e.g. this post has it’s own HTML (Hypertext Markup Language) file associated with it. Hugo, Jeykll and Hexo are the static site generators that you pass these files to. The main advantage to static websites is that you can hit the ground running, a little bit of HTML and CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) knowledge can go a long way. There is no requirement to know any server side scripting languages such a PHP (Hypertext Preprocessor) or SQL (Structured Query Language), which means there is no server-host interaction and therefore load times are very quick. There are drawbacks though. If you intend to change something on every page, then this can be very time consuming. There is also a lot less functionality comapared to a dynamic page which gives you the ability to add features such as shopping carts and social media interactions. Another option would have been to use a CMS (Content Management System) such as Joomla or Wordpress, beating both static and dynamic on ease of setup and time to update. Although I feel that their functionality is a black box and if you want to deviate from the default template then you may get unstuck. CMS’s have got around this by adding plugins. However I have found that often these aren’t available on the cheaper pricing tiers. For example Wordpress does not allow you to use iframe (a webpage inside another webpage…webception) and adding a plugin is only available on the business pricing tier (£20.83 a month). So I’d argue that a static website for a blog is a good option, which allows the website to grow as the webmaster’s skills do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all my posts, I’m writing from memory, from my own experiences, which may have not been remembered correctly or do not include the full picture. If you think there should be an improvement to the post then please get in touch and I’ll update it, I’m always willing to learn!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rshiny Weather App</title>
      <link>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rshiny-weather-app/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
