<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gis on Mark Cherrie</title>
    <link>/tags/gis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gis on Mark Cherrie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/gis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Earth Engine: NDVI in Scotland 2001-2017</title>
      <link>/post/gee/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gee/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Motivation I’m interested in a long-term small-area level measure of ‘green spaces’, features of the natural environment that are important for a wide variety of health outcomes.
 Green spaces over time There are two major green space datasets for Scotland, Scotland’s Greenspace Map 2011 and the Ordnance Survey’s Greenspace Map 2017. These maps were produced by characterising OS polygons using aerial photos, with the latter updated every 6 months from July 2017.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapzen Isochrone Maps</title>
      <link>/post/isochrone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/isochrone/</guid>
      <description>I have just come across Mapzen’s routing engine (Valhalla), which can be used to produce incredible isochrone maps, mentioned in this blog post. If you’ve not heard of Mapzen they provide mapping tools for developers so that their websites can be converted to the spatial side. The neat thing about isochrone lines is that they show the boundary around a point where travel time is equal. So you can ask some interesting proximity based questions (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStreetMap in R</title>
      <link>/post/osmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/osmr/</guid>
      <description>I found a really helpful tutorial on using OpenStreetMap data in R the other day.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>