<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tobacco on Mark Cherrie</title>
    <link>http://www.markcherrie.net/tags/tobacco/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tobacco on Mark Cherrie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/tobacco/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring changes in the built environment: tobacco retailers in Scotland</title>
      <link>http://www.markcherrie.net/post/tobaccoretailerchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markcherrie.net/post/tobaccoretailerchange/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The built environment is constantly changing. Whether it be short-term changes - e.g. roadworks, or long-term, e.g. a new road. These changes can impact exposures (air pollutants from road traffic), behaviours (decision to drive to work) or health (risk of being in a traffic accident). It’s therefore important to monitor the changes to the built environment so that interventions can be developed to reduce risk to health either directly or indirectly (exposure/behaviour). Monitoring the built environment can be done through remote sensing, surveying, crowdsourcing or administrative data collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;remote-sensing&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Remote Sensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satellites can be equipped with instruments that collect information on reflected light, which can be used to infer &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.markcherrie.net/post/gee/&#34;&gt;changes in vegetation&lt;/a&gt; and therefore by the inverse - the (non-vegetated) built environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;surveying&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Surveying&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mixture or remote sensing (aerial photography) and surveying is used to create the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/about/what-we-do&#34;&gt;Ordnance Survey’s (OS) databases&lt;/a&gt;. The OS Open Map Local data has been used by the CRESH/SPHSU team to map changes in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cresh.org.uk/2019/08/02/an-atlas-of-change-in-scotlands-built-environment-2016-17/&#34;&gt;buildings, roads and woodlands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;crowdsourcing&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crowdsourcing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fixmystreet.com/&#34;&gt;FixMyStreet&lt;/a&gt; website was developed using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mysociety/fixmystreet&#34;&gt;web-based reporting platform&lt;/a&gt; by the group - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mysociety.org/&#34;&gt;MySociety&lt;/a&gt;. This website enables people to record local problems, e.g. graffiti, fly tipping, broken paving slabs, or street lighting. Researchers can use this data to see how ‘problems’ in the built environment change over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;administrative-data-collection&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Administrative data collection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we might use data collected by local and national government. The CRESH team used this kind of information to populate the database on location of &lt;a href=&#34;https://creshmap.com/shiny/alcoholtobacco/&#34;&gt;alcohol and tobacco retailers in Scotland&lt;/a&gt;. This webmap visualises the data for 2012 and 2016. The alcohol retailer data was collected manually by requesting licensing information from each of the 32 Scottish local authorities. The tobacco retailer data was collected by querying a centralised register, available online. Therefore for tobacco retailers we can assess change at shorter time intervals by regularly querying the online database. This blogpost uses the register for two aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aims&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aims&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a way to automatically download records of tobacco retailers in Scotland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess change in tobacco retailers over time (shorter interval than previously - 1 year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;method&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Tobacco and Primary Medical Services (Scotland) Act 2010, it became law that all tobacco retailers were required to register on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tobaccoregisterscotland.org/&#34;&gt;Scottish Tobacco Retailer Register (STRR)&lt;/a&gt;. From the 1 October 2017, all nicotine vapour retailers also had to register. A person who breaches the act three times in a two year period is banned (for upto 12 months) from the register and therefore selling tobacco in Scotland. An R script was created to download the tobacco register.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(&amp;#39;rvest&amp;#39;)

# Specify the URL and then read the html
url &amp;lt;- &amp;#39;https://www.tobaccoregisterscotland.org/search-the-register/?Name=&amp;amp;Postcode=&amp;amp;LocalAuthority=&amp;amp;BusinessType=&amp;amp;ProductType=&amp;amp;PremisesStatus=&amp;#39;
webpage &amp;lt;- read_html(url)

# calculate the number of records then do a look with all the pages!
Numberofrecords &amp;lt;- html_nodes(webpage,&amp;#39;.premises-search-results__total&amp;#39;)
Numberofrecords &amp;lt;- html_text(Numberofrecords)
Numberofrecords &amp;lt;- readr::parse_number(Numberofrecords)

# iteratre over the pages, extracting the bits that we need
STRR_df&amp;lt;-NULL
pages&amp;lt;-round(as.numeric(Numberofrecords)/20,0)+1
for(i in seq(1:pages)){
  url &amp;lt;- paste0(&amp;#39;https://www.tobaccoregisterscotland.org/search-the-register/?Name=&amp;amp;Postcode=&amp;amp;LocalAuthority=&amp;amp;BusinessType=&amp;amp;ProductType=&amp;amp;PremisesStatus=&amp;amp;page=&amp;#39;, i)
  webpage &amp;lt;- read_html(url)
  Address &amp;lt;- html_nodes(webpage,&amp;#39;dd:nth-child(2)&amp;#39;)
  LocalAuthority &amp;lt;- html_nodes(webpage,&amp;#39;dd:nth-child(4)&amp;#39;)
  BusinessType &amp;lt;- html_nodes(webpage,&amp;#39;dd:nth-child(6)&amp;#39;)
  ProductSold &amp;lt;-html_nodes(webpage,&amp;#39;dd:nth-child(8)&amp;#39;)
  CompanyName &amp;lt;-html_nodes(webpage,&amp;quot;dd:nth-child(10)&amp;quot;)
  Status &amp;lt;-html_nodes(webpage,&amp;quot;dd:nth-child(12)&amp;quot;)
  
  # make into text
  Address &amp;lt;- html_text(Address)
  LocalAuthority &amp;lt;- html_text(LocalAuthority)
  BusinessType &amp;lt;- html_text(BusinessType)
  ProductSold &amp;lt;- html_text(ProductSold)
  CompanyName &amp;lt;- html_text(CompanyName)
  Status &amp;lt;- html_text(Status)
  
  # combine
  STRR&amp;lt;-as.data.frame(cbind(Address,LocalAuthority, BusinessType,ProductSold, CompanyName,Status))
  STRR$Address&amp;lt;-as.character(STRR$Address)
  STRR$Address&amp;lt;-paste0(STRR$Address, &amp;quot;, Scotland&amp;quot;)
  STRR_df&amp;lt;-rbind(STRR_df, STRR)
}

write.csv(STRR_df,paste0(&amp;quot;data/STRR_&amp;quot;, Sys.Date(), &amp;quot;.csv&amp;quot;), row.names=F)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then use the ‘setdiff’ function to compare two downloads of the STRR database:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;STRR06&amp;lt;-read.csv(&amp;quot;data/STRR_2019-06-26.csv&amp;quot;)
STRR09&amp;lt;-read.csv(&amp;quot;data/STRR_2019-09-25.csv&amp;quot;)

diff &amp;lt;- data.frame(Address=setdiff(STRR09$Address, STRR06$Address))
STRRdiff&amp;lt;-merge(diff, STRR09, by=&amp;quot;Address&amp;quot;, all.x=T)

library(ggplot2)

STRRdiff %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(BusinessType)) +
  geom_bar() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle =75, hjust = 1))

ggsave(&amp;quot;output/BusinessTypeChange.png&amp;quot;)

STRRdiff %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(LocalAuthority)) +
  geom_bar() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 75, hjust = 1))

ggsave(&amp;quot;output/LocalAuthorityChange.png&amp;quot;)

STRRdiff %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(ProductSold)) +
  geom_bar() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 75, hjust = 1))

ggsave(&amp;quot;output/ProductSold.png&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;results&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the 25th of June and 26th of September 2019, there were 187 additions to the STRR. The local authority with the greatest increase was Glasgow with 40 retailers, followed by Edinburgh and North Lanarkshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/SRTT_images/LocalAuthorityChange.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of the increase (87 retailers) was from ‘Convenience stores’, but a notable increase was found in ‘Other retail’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/SRTT_images/BusinessTypeChange.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of retailers who had newly registered were selling both tobacco and nicotine vapour. Interestingly, there were more new registrations for nicotine vapour products only compared to tobacco only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/SRTT_images/ProductSold.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This analysis shows the potential of monitoring places using administrative data. Patterns over a three month period were described and show differences in tobacco retailing in Scotland by geography, type of product and type of retailer. Future work will supplement previous analysis on &lt;a href=&#34;https://tobaccocontrol.bmj.com/content/early/2019/01/28/tobaccocontrol-2018-054543.info&#34;&gt;tobacco retailer change in scotland&lt;/a&gt;, with more granular measures of change, which could be used to act, in a more timely manner, on clustering of products (i.e. availability of tobacco) in deprived areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DISPLAY: Determining the impact of smoking point of sale legislation among youth (Display) study</title>
      <link>http://www.markcherrie.net/project/display/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markcherrie.net/project/display/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alcohol and Tobacco Environments in Scotland</title>
      <link>http://www.markcherrie.net/project/webmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markcherrie.net/project/webmap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I led the re-development of the CRESH &lt;a href=&#34;https://creshmap.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;webmap&lt;/a&gt;, which was originally launched in 2015. This app was designed to allow users to map tobacco and alcohol outlet density, and related health outcomes for small areas in Scotland (i.e. datazones, which represent around 5,000 residents).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is increasing evidence which shows that the density of tobacco and alcohol retailers has an effect on both smoking/drinking behaviours but also the associated morbidity/mortality. For example those living in areas with the highest density of retailers have double the alcohol-related death rate; and adolescents living in areas with the highest density of tobacco retailers are 50% more likely to smoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alcohol retailer data was collected from representatives of the 32 local authorities, and required months of cleaning to have it ready for the webmap. In the redevelopment we tried to make the information accessible and clearly presented. In addition, we really pushed to make the data easy to download, to empower local communities so that they are more involved in the decisions on the built environment surrounding their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CRESH webmap was created in partnership with Alcohol Focus Scotland (AFS) and Action on Smoking and Health Scotland (ASH Scotland). The original research was funded by the Scottish Collaboration for Public Health Research and Policy and we have received funding from the Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC) to publicise our research and make it more accessible to the public and policy makers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
