<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tobacco on Mark Cherrie</title>
    <link>/tags/tobacco/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tobacco on Mark Cherrie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/tobacco/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring changes in the built environment: tobacco retailers in Scotland</title>
      <link>/post/tobaccoretailerchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tobaccoretailerchange/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The built environment is constantly changing. Whether it be short-term changes - e.g. roadworks, or long-term, e.g. a new road. These changes can impact exposures (air pollutants from road traffic), behaviours (decision to drive to work) or health (risk of being in a traffic accident). It’s therefore important to monitor the changes to the built environment so that interventions can be developed to reduce risk to health either directly or indirectly (exposure/behaviour).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DISPLAY: Determining the impact of smoking point of sale legislation among youth (Display) study</title>
      <link>/project/display/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/display/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alcohol and Tobacco Environments in Scotland</title>
      <link>/project/webmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/webmap/</guid>
      <description>I led the re-development of the CRESH webmap, which was originally launched in 2015. This app was designed to allow users to map tobacco and alcohol outlet density, and related health outcomes for small areas in Scotland (i.e. datazones, which represent around 5,000 residents).
There is increasing evidence which shows that the density of tobacco and alcohol retailers has an effect on both smoking/drinking behaviours but also the associated morbidity/mortality. For example those living in areas with the highest density of retailers have double the alcohol-related death rate; and adolescents living in areas with the highest density of tobacco retailers are 50% more likely to smoke.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>