<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Visualisation on Mark Cherrie</title>
    <link>/categories/data-visualisation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Visualisation on Mark Cherrie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mark Cherrie</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/data-visualisation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Geography of the Revoke Article 50 petition</title>
      <link>/post/geography_of_the_revoke_article_50_petition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/geography_of_the_revoke_article_50_petition/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The ‘Revoke article 50 and remain in the EU petition’ is the most popular petition ever, which aims to stop the brexit process. The rules are that after 10,000 signatures, petitions get a response from the government, after 100,000 signatures, petitions are considered for debate in Parliament and after 17.4 million, we stop Brexit (Andrea Leadsom, 2019). As of writing this (25/03/19 17:00 GMT), the petition has amassed over 5 million signatures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to quickly visualise massive spatio-temporal data</title>
      <link>/post/uber-kepler/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/uber-kepler/</guid>
      <description>Background Are you collecting lots of geospatial data and need a way to quickly visualise what you’ve got? Read on! I had this problem; I was collecting a lot of information on my daily movements from Arc App: Location and Activity (more on the use of Arc for research later). Additionally, I wanted to quickly see what features of the urban environment (e.g. greenspaces) I was being ‘exposed’ to. The solution was Uber’s open source geospatial analysis tool: Kepler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Devolved parliaments and assemblies Legislation</title>
      <link>/post/devolvedlegislation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/devolvedlegislation/</guid>
      <description>Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland have had devolved powers since 1997, 1997 and 1998 respectively. During this time 480 Acts have been passed, an act being defined as primary legislation which has been through several stages from:
Pre-legislative scrutiny on the draft piece of legislation (bill)First Reading - first presentation, no votingSecond Reading - debate on principles, votingCommittee Stage - Considers bill clausesConsideration or report stage - Consider further amendmentsThird Reading - Consider final textPassage - Sent to other house (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Green Space and Traffic in Glasgow</title>
      <link>/post/greentraffic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/greentraffic/</guid>
      <description>Background The health benefit of greater availability of greenspaces is mediated by the quality of these spaces (Zhang et al., 2017). Recently, quality was associated with psychological distress, whereas availability had no effect (Feng and Astell-Burt, 2018). Both of these measures of quality were self-reported. Another method to determine quality is from GIS-derived measures of land use. Perhaps the optimal method is using questionnaire self-report and GIS-derived measures as has been developed by (Stessens et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapzen Isochrone Maps</title>
      <link>/post/isochrone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/isochrone/</guid>
      <description>I have just come across Mapzen’s routing engine (Valhalla), which can be used to produce incredible isochrone maps, mentioned in this blog post. If you’ve not heard of Mapzen they provide mapping tools for developers so that their websites can be converted to the spatial side. The neat thing about isochrone lines is that they show the boundary around a point where travel time is equal. So you can ask some interesting proximity based questions (e.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>